Lesson 17 A man-made disease
人为的疾病
First listen and then answer the following question.
听录音,然后回答以下问题.
myxomatosis: n.  多发性粘液瘤
What factor helped to spread the disease of myxomatosis?
什么因素助长了多发性粘液瘤疾病的蔓延?
settlement: n.  新拓居地
In the early days of the settlement of Australia,
在澳大利亚移民初期,
settler: n.  移居者
enterprising settlers unwisely introduced the European rabbit.
一些有创业精神的移民不明智地把欧洲兔子引进了澳大利亚.
Antipodes: n.  新西兰和澳大利亚（英）
This rabbit had no natural enemies in the Antipodes,
这种兔子在澳大利亚及新西兰没有天敌,
abandon: n.  放任，纵情
so that it multiplied with that promiscuous abandon characteristic of rabbits.
因此便以兔子所特有的杂乱交配迅猛繁殖起来.
It overran a whole continent.
整个澳洲兔子成灾.
devastation: n.  破坏，劫掠, burrow: v.  挖、掘
It caused devastation by burrowing and by devouring the herbage
它们在地下打洞,
which might have maintained millions of sheep and cattle.
吃掉本可以饲养数百万头牛羊的牧草,造成毁灭性的破坏.
Scientists discovered that this particular variety of rabbit,
科学家们发现,这种特殊品种的兔子，
(and apparently no other animal)
(显然不包括别的动物)
virus: n.  病毒, myxomatosis: n.  多发性粘液瘤
was susceptible to a fatal virus disease, myxomatosis.
易患一种叫做"多发性粘液瘤"的致命病毒性疾病.
burrow: v.  挖、掘, infect: v.  传染
By infecting animals and letting them loose in the burrows,
通过让染上此病的动物在洞内乱跑,
epidemic: n.  流行病
local epidemics of this disease could be created.
就可以使这种疾病在一个地区蔓延起来.
mosquito: n.  蚊虫
Later it was found that there was a type of mosquito,
后来又发现,有一种蚊子，
carrier: n.  带菌者
which acted as the carrier of this disease and passed it on to the rabbits.
充当了传播这种疾病的媒介,能把此病传染给兔子.
mosquito: n.  蚊虫
So while the rest of the world was trying to get rid of mosquitoes,
因此,世界上其他地方在设法消灭蚊子的时候,
Australia was encouraging this one.
澳大利亚却在促使这种蚊子大量繁殖.
It effectively spread the disease all over the continent,
蚊子把这种疾病扩散到整个澳洲大陆,
and drastically reduced the rabit population.
效果甚佳,结果兔子的数目大为减少.
It later became apparent
后来,明显看出,
that rabbits were developing a degree of resistance to this disease,
兔子对这种疾病产生了一定程度的免疫力,
exterminate: v.  消灭
so that the rabbit population was unlike- ly to be completely exterminated.
所以兔子不可能被完全消灭.
There were hopes,howe- ver,that the problem of the rabbit would become manageable.
但是,已有希望解决兔子所带来的问题.
bequeath: v.  把...传给, pest: n.  害虫，有害动物
Ironically,Europe, which had bequeathed the rabbit as a pest to Australia,
具有讽刺意味的是,欧洲把这种兔子作为有害动物传给澳洲,
pest: n.  害虫，有害动物, pestilence: n.  瘟疫
acquired this man-made disease as a pestilence.
而欧洲自己却染上了这种为人的瘟疫般的疾病.
A French physician decided to get rid of the wild rabbits on his own estate
一位法国内科医生决定除掉自己庄园内的野兔,
myxomatosis: n.  多发性粘液瘤
and introduced myxomatosis.
引进了多发性粘液瘤疾病。
confine: n.  范围
It did not,however, remain within the confines of this estate.
然而,这种疾病并未被局限在他的庄园内,
It spread through France,
结果在整个法国蔓延开来 ,
pest: n.  害虫，有害动物
where wild rabbits are not generally regarded as a pest
野兔在法国一般不被当作有害动物,
but as a sport and a useful food supply,
而被视为打猎的玩物和有用的食物来源,
pest: n.  害虫，有害动物
and it spread to Britain where wild rabbits are regarded as a pest
这种疾病又蔓延到了英国.在英国,野兔被当作有害动物,
domesticate: v.  驯养
but where domesticated rabbits,equally susceptible to the disease,
可是同样易感染这种疾病的家兔，
are the basis of a profitable fur industry.
却是赚钱的毛皮工业的基础.
The question became one of whether Man could control the dis- ease he had invented.
现在的问题是,人类能否控制住这种人为的疾病.